Autumn of the 24th year of Yuankang
元康二十四年の秋
Prince of Jin Sikong Yao ascended the throne as emperor
晋の王司空曜が即位して帝と称する
Posthumously honored late emperor Sikong Jing as Xuan Yuan Emperor
追封先帝司空景を宣元帝とする
Enfeoffed Sikong Sheng as crown prince
司空盛を太子に冊立する
Posthumously honored Lady Xie as Virtuous and Cultured Empress
謝氏を淑徳文皇后として追尊する
Enfeoffed Chen family's eldest daughter as consort
陳氏の長女を夫人に立てる
Rank second to the empress
ウェイヤージャオティン
Harmonious in the palace
宮中を調和させることを許す
I, Sikong Yao
臣シクウヨウ
Kneel and report to ancestors and heaven
祖先と天地に告げ知らせる
Since
自
After the Jianping rebellion
建平の乱の後
The Wuzhao invaded
ウーウーの侵入
Disrupted our land
我が国の山河を乱す
I, being of Xuan's bloodline
臣はすでに宣室の血脈であります
Should bear the ancestral state
肩に先祖と国家の責任を担う
And care for the people
天下の民を心配する
Thus defeated Shilang at Yiyang
遂に弋陽で石狼を打ち破った
Recovered the homeland in the north
北の境地に故郷を取り戻す
Old people
旧民の長老
All wept
次々と涙を流す
Saying
咸といふ
Never thought to see the imperial army again today
今日また官軍を見ることを望まない
After
後
The court bred traitors
朝は裏切り者や裏切り者がいた
Acting perversely
逆行して行動する
Yao
輝く
Following ancestral teachings
祖先の教えを慎んで守る
Raised troops in anger
奮起して兵を興す
To seek state stability
国家の安定を求めるために
Now
今
Above, for heaven and earth's will
上は天地の心である
Below, for the people's support
以下は元元に帰属します
Set altar to worship heaven
祭壇を設けて天に祈る
Announce to all under heaven
天下に告げる
Inherit the great succession
大統を継ぐ
Change era name
元号の改元
Longwu
隆武
Long live Your Majesty
陛下万歳
Reward
賞
Xie Jian'an
シャケンアン
Authority commands respect
威厳で人々を服従させる
Merit surpasses all ministers
功績が群臣を凌ぐ
Promote to Minister over the Masses
司徒に進む
Enfeoff as Duke of Qing
封慶国公
Appoint as Chancellor
丞相に拝謁する
Command Six Ministries and Nine Courts
六部九卿を統括する
Record Secretariat affairs
尚書の事柄を記録する
Govern Jingzhou
京州の牧を領する
Zu Yue
ソゲツ
Loyal and humble
公正で忠実謙虚である
Brave and resolute
勇敢で不屈
Promote to General of Agile Cavalry
進骠騎将軍
Enfeoff as Marquis of Wuwu
武威侯に封じられる
Govern Dingzhou
州牧を任命する
Command all military affairs in the north
北地の諸軍事を都督する
Xie Xuan
謝玄
Outmaneuvers enemies
敵を知り勝利を制する
Skilled in both civil and military
文武両道
Enfeoff as Marquis of Yongning
永寧侯に封じる
Appoint as Secretariat Gentleman
尚書郎に任じられる
Concurrently Grand Tutor to the Crown Prince
兼任太子太傅
Hold rank of Grandee of the Palace
光禄大夫を務める
Grant gold seal and purple ribbon
加金章紫綬
Zhu Yuanzhi
朱元之
Steady and strategic
沈着で計略に長けている
Brave and decisive
勇貴は断つことができる
Enfeoff as General Who Guards the North
封鎮北将軍
Appoint as Grand Commandant
太尉に拝謁する
Govern Qing, Yan, Ping, and Liang prefectures
青燕を治め平梁四州を牧する
Strike first to gain advantage
先に手を打つ方が有利だよ
Posthumously honor
追う
Late Great General Zu Kun
故大将軍ソコン
As Loyal and Martial Guardian Duke
忠武国公に仕える
To be enshrined in the ancestral temple
太廟に供え物を捧げる
Build temple and establish worship
祠を建てて祭る
Posthumously honor
追う
Late Colonel Director of Retainers Chu Huan
前司隷校尉楚桓
As Marquis of Dingxiang
定郷侯に任命する
His son Chu Meng
その子楚蒙
Appoint as Colonel of the Feathered Forest
羽林校尉に授ける
Command capital guard
京城を守る任に就く
Inherit title for three generations
三世を継ぐ
Posthumously honor
追う
Late Liu Dadao as Marquis of Wuyi
故劉大刀は武毅侯であった
Grant Liu Nian as Zhaoyi
劉念に昭儀の位を賜る
Enter the empress's quarters
入室の椒房
Posthumously honor
追う
Late Director of the Imperial Academy Yugong as Grand Preceptor
故国子監祭酒虞宮は太保となる
His disciple Wang Ming promoted to Censor-in-Chief
その弟子の王明は御史大夫に抜擢された
Qiu Sheng enfeoffed as Count of Yunxian
丘勝が雲県伯に封じられる
Grant one thousand bolts of silk
絹千匹を賜る
Command Beishuo Army as Major
北朔軍の司馬を務める
Qi Jiu and Lin Shu appointed as Left and Right Guard Colonels
斉の九林戍は左右の護軍校尉に授けられる
Each granted bright armor and ring-pommel sword
各々賜りし明光の鎧環首の刀
Guard the palace
宮殿の衛兵
Posthumously honor late Vice Minister of Revenue Cao Biaozhi
故人である戸部侍郎の曹表を追贈する
As Marquis of Nanxiang, Cultured and Loyal
文忠南郷侯として
Announce far and wide
布告が遠くまで伝わる
Let all know
全て知らせるようにする
Let those in charge implement
主体が実行する
Jiazi day, October of the 24th year of Yuankang
元康二十四年十月甲子